<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>jpowcode - Making</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/making.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2021-01-06T10:20:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>Some Lockdown Builds</title><link href="/A%20few%20quick%20builds%20during%20the%20lock-down.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-01-06T10:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-06T10:20:00+00:00</updated><author><name>jpowcode</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-01-06:/A few quick builds during the lock-down.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;USing some spare time and some scrap materials to build a few things.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;With plenty of spare time on my hands and a garage full of scrap bits and bobs I made a few things. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phone or tablet stand&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
For watching YouTube whilst lying on the sofa. Also useful for Video calls. Simply made from some scrap plywood and some hinges I had knocking about. I put bits of bicycle handlbar tape on the bottom to stop it scratching the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 1_1" src="./images/tablet_stand.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bee box&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
For attracting Bees to the garden. I had loads of oak lying about for years after a few mishaps whilst building a bookcase.  The hexagonal design is supposed to mirror the shape of the cells within a beehive. It's currently filled with some drilled out bits of wood in various diameter holes and some roled up bits of paper. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 2_1" src="./images/bee_box1.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 2_2" src="./images/bee_box2.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dice shield&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
For stopping dice going everywhere whilst playing board games. I also wanted to practice some finger joints on my router.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 3_1" src="./images/dice_shield1.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 3_2" src="./images/dice_shield2.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
For lounging in the garden during the nice sunny whether (summer lockdown, not winter lockdown). Lots of old bike wheels knocking about and random bits of wood. I made the legs by cutting a bike wheel rim into thirds and bolting them together. The centre piece is bit of old bike seat tube cut down. The surface has a few coats of outdoor varnish on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 4_1" src="./images/table1.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 4_2" src="./images/table2.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 4_3" src="./images/table3.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Card wallet&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br/&gt;
For carrying my cards. Two bits of metal with some sewn elastic to hold them together and allow the cards to be pushed out. Simple but quite effective. The metal is reassuringly heavy! I also made an emergency pound coin holder. The left two most images are the prototype I made out of plastic to see what it was carrying it around before committing to making one out of metal. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 5_1" src="./images/wallet1.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 5_2" src="./images/wallet2.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;img alt="Image 5_3" src="./images/wallet3.jpg"/&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content><category term="Making"></category><category term="Making"></category></entry><entry><title>Non Transitive Dice</title><link href="/non-transitive-dice.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-04-20T22:24:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-20T22:24:00+01:00</updated><author><name>jpowcode</name></author><id>tag:None,2020-04-20:/non-transitive-dice.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Making a set of special dice&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;html&gt;&lt;body&gt;&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine wanted to use some special dice called non transitive dice
with his maths class at school to help with the teaching of probability.
As et of three dice are considered to be non transitive if the probability
that the first dice rolls higher than the second is more than half, the probability
that the second rolls more than the third is more than half but the probability
that the third rolls more than the first is not more than half. There is a
more detailed explanation &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nontransitive_dice"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He couldn't find any at a reasonable enough price to enable him to buy
enough for a class of 30 pupils to experiment with so he asked me if
could make some. I decided to give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First problem: how to make small cubes with rounded edges with enough
accuracy that they roll well and are not biased.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After bit of experimenting with cutting them out of wood with a table
saw and sanding the edges I decided this was neither going to be easy
or accurate. I toyed with the idea of laser cutting or using a CNC machine,
but really I wanted a solution that was not going to take a huge amount of time.
eBay to the rescue: I bought some blank dice from
China. A bag of 20 odd for not much money. First problem solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second problem: how to mark the dice with the numbers accurately enough that
they look professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried marking out dots like on a traditional dice but again, getting accuracy was
difficult. Any slight inaccuracy was very noticeable. Then I tried hand
writing the numbers. This gave a much more natural look. Second problem
solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third problem: Just writing on the dice with permanent marker tended to rub
off over time. To solve this I first wrote on the dice with a marker, then
went over the marker with a small engraving tool in a Dremel. This took
the shiny surface off the dice. I finished by going over these again with
the permanent marker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="/images/nt_dice.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="alternate text" class="align-middle" src="images/nt_dice.jpg" style="width: 400px;"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content><category term="Making"></category><category term="Making"></category></entry></feed>